[Stories from the Sea]
[Fish Tale
My Secret Life as Plankton /ˈplæŋktən/]
How did I get here?
Well, it's a stranger story
than you might think.
I came from a world of drifters /ˈdrɪftə 漂流者/,
a place few humans have ever seen.
The world of plankton.
I came from a batch /bætʃ/ of a million eggs,
and only a few of us survived.
When I became a larva /ˈlɑːvə/,
I moved among other drifters.
["Plankton" comes from the Greek
"planktos" for wandering /ˈwɒndərɪŋ 流浪的/]
My fellow plankton came in all sizes,
from tiny algae /ˈældʒi 藻类/ and bacteria
to animals longer than a blue whale.
I shared my nursery /ˈnɜːsrɪ 婴儿室/
with other embryos /ˈɛmbrɪˌəʊ 胚胎/ and juveniles /ˈdʒuvəˌnaɪl 幼态生物/,
from clams /klæm 蛤/ and crabs /kræb 蟹/
to sea urchins /ˈɜːtʃɪn 顽童 / 海胆 and anemones /əˈnemənɪ 海葵/.
(High pitch /pɪtʃ 达到高潮/ sound)
We drifting animals
are called zooplankton.
The most common animals here
are copepods /ˈkəʊpɪˌpɒd 桡足动物/ and krill /krɪl 磷虾/.
(Buzzing)
You could search the world over,
but you'd never find a place
more diverse /daɪˈvɜ:s 多样的/ than my childhood home.
A teaspoon of seawater
can contain more
than a million living creatures.
It can be a pretty tough
existence, though.
Trillions are born here,
but only a few make it to adulthood /ˈædʌltˌhʊd/.
He may be no larger than a pin /pɪn 大头针/ head,
but this crab larva
is an arrow /ˈærəʊ 箭头/ worm's worst nightmare.
(Bumping noises)
(Buzzing)
Epic /ˈɛpɪk 史诗般的/ battles between carnivores /ˈkɑːnɪˌvɔː 食肉动物/
like these are just one way to get food.
But the real powers
of this place come from phytoplankton /ˌfaɪtəˈplæŋktən 浮游植物/.
Single-celled life
that transforms sunlight
and carbon dioxide /daɪˈɒksaɪd 二氧化物/
into edible gold.
Phytoplankton /ˌfaɪtəˈplæŋktən 浮游植物/ are the base
for the largest food web in the world.
During the night,
many animals like me
would rise up from the depths
to feed on this sun-powered feast /fiːst 盛宴/.
(Maraca sound)
I was part of the largest daily
migration /maɪˈɡreɪʃən/ of life on Earth.
During the day,
I'd return to the darkness,
where I'd join my bizarre /bɪˈzɑː 古怪的/ companions /kəmˈpænjən 同伴/.
(High pitch buzz)
(Flapping noises)
Cannibals /ˈkænɪbəl 吃同类的动物/, like this
sea butterfly mollusk /ˈmɒləsk 软体动物/,
that eats its next of kin /kɪn 同族/.
And comb /kəʊm 梳子/ jellies /ˈdʒɛlɪ 果冻 水母/,
that beat cilia /ˈsɪlɪə 纤毛/ like rainbowed eyelashes /ˈaɪˌlæʃ 睫毛/.
Some of these snare /snɛə 套索/
their prey /preɪ 猎物/ with sticky /ˈstɪkɪ 粘性的/ tentacles /ˈtɛntəkəl 触须/,
while others just take
a bite out of their cousins.
And siphonophores /ˈsaɪfənəˌfɔː 管水母/
that catch prey with toxic /ˈtɒksɪk/ fishing lures /lʊə 诱饵/.
But my favorite would have
to be the crustacean /krʌˈsteɪʃən 甲壳类/ Phronima.
Its monstrous /ˈmɒnstrəs 可怕的/ looks inspired
the movie "Aliens."
It can catch tiny bits in its bristles /ˈbrɪsəl 刚毛/,
but prefers larger prey like salps /sælp 樽海鞘/.
With two sets of eyes,
this female prowls /praʊl 潜行/ the deeper water.
Prey in hand,
she performs one
of the strangest behaviors
in the entire /ɪnˈtaɪə 全部的/ animal kingdom.
With body parts from her victims,
she delicately /ˈdelɪkətlɪ 精致地/ assembles
a barrel/ˈbærəl 桶/-like home
feeding her young until they can drift off
and survive on their own.
Best of all, they make the perfect
snack for a small fish like me.
Here among the plankton,
the food web is so tangled /ˈtæŋɡəld 纠缠的/ and complex,
even scientists don't know who eats whom.
But I do.
At least now you know a bit of my story.
There's so much more to me
than just a tasty meal.